<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Virginalia. or Spirituall sonnets in prayse of the most glorious Virgin Marie vpon euerie seuerall title of her litanies of Loreto: all or most part of the principall passages therein confirmed by the euident testimonies of the ancient fathers, to preuent the obiections of such, as vsually detract from her deserued prayses. By I.B.</title>
            <author>I. B., fl. 1632.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1632</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16707</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3608.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104683</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840416</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840416</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4919</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16707)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4919)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1128:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Virginalia. or Spirituall sonnets in prayse of the most glorious Virgin Marie vpon euerie seuerall title of her litanies of Loreto: all or most part of the principall passages therein confirmed by the euident testimonies of the ancient fathers, to preuent the obiections of such, as vsually detract from her deserued prayses. By I.B.</title>
                  <author>I. B., fl. 1632.</author>
                  <author>Anderton, Lawrence, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Anderton, James, fl. 1624, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed with licence [by the widow of N. Courant],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Rouen] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1632.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I.B. has been identified as John Brereley, who has been identified as both James Anderton and Lawrence Anderton; but the attribution is probably incorrect. See "Recusant history" XVI (1982), p. 17-41.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Identification of printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 3539 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary, --  Blessed Virgin, Saint --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4919:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4919:1"/>
            <p>VIRGINALIA OR SPIRITVALL SONNETS in prayſe of the moſt Glorious VIRGIN MARIE, vpon euerie ſeuerall Title of her Litanies of Loreto: <hi>All or moſt part of the principall paſſages therein confirmed by the euident teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the ancient Fathers, to preuent the obiections of ſuch, as vſually detract from her deſerued prayſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By I. B.</p>
            <q>
               <p>What is more noble then the Mother of God; what more glorious then she, whome Glorie hath choſen?  <bibl>
                     <hi>S. Ambr. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Virg.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed with Licence. 1632.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="list">
            <pb facs="tcp:4919:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4919:2"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of ſuch Fathers, as hereafter are alleadged; togeather with the age, they liued in.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Iuſtinus Martyr, liued Anno Domini <hi>150.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Origenes. <hi>130.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gregorius Neocaeſarienſis Thaumaturgus. <hi>260.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Methodius Tyri Epiſcopus. <hi>260.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Athanaſius. <hi>340.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ambroſius. <hi>370.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ephrem Syrus. <hi>370.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gregorius Nazianzenus. <hi>380.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Epiphanius. <hi>380.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gregorius Nyſſenus. <hi>380.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hieronymus. <hi>390.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ruffinus. <hi>390.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Auguſtinus. <hi>400.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chryſoſtomus. <hi>400.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sophronius Hieroſolymitanus ſenior. <hi>400.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Proclus Conſtantinopolitanus. <hi>430.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cyrillus Alexandrinus. <hi>430.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Petrus Chryſologus. <hi>440.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Leo Magnus. <hi>450.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Theodoretus. <hi>450.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:4919:3"/>
               <item>Concilium Calcedonenſe. <hi>453.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Titus Boſtrenſis Epiſcopus. <hi>460.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Baſilius Seleucius. <hi>460.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cryſippus Hieroſolymitanus Presbyter. <hi>500.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fulgentius. <hi>500.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Euthymius Eremita. <hi>540.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Andreas Cretenſis Epiſcopus. <hi>560.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Heſychius Hieroſolymitanus. <hi>580.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gregorius Magnus. <hi>590.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Eutychianus. <hi>600.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Iſidorus Hiſpalenſis. <hi>620.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sergius Hierapolita. <hi>640.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Beda. <hi>700.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ioannes Damaſcenus. <hi>730.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Alcuinus Anglus. <hi>750.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Elias Cretenſis. <hi>780.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Idiota. <hi>800.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Anſelmus Cantuarienſis. <hi>1080.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Bernardus. <hi>1130.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4919:3"/>
            <head>Virginalia, or, Spirituall Sonnets, in prayſe of the moſt glorious Virgin MARIE vpon euerie ſeuerall Title of her Litanies of Loreto.</head>
            <div n="1" type="sonnet">
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 1. SANCTA MARIA.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MARIA,<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Maria is interpreted Starre of the ſea: and she as a remarkable ſtarre shines brightly by the grace of a ſpeciall priuiledge among the waues of this wauering world. &amp;c. S. Bed. ad Euangel. in feſto Annunc. Maria.</note> glorious ſea-ſtarre; thy cleare ſight</l>
                  <l>Guides vs vpon the world's tempeſtuous waues;</l>
                  <l>And through the dreadfull ſhades of ſinn's darke night</l>
                  <l>In th' port of bliſſe our craſie veſſel ſaues.</l>
                  <l>Thy ſacred name moſt aptly doth inferre</l>
                  <l>A bitter ſea, t'expreſſe thy ſeas of greef,</l>
                  <l>when thou beheldſt thy Sonne, who could not erre,</l>
                  <l>As faultie dye, iudg'd worſer then a theef.</l>
                  <l>Well art thou<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Maria, which is interpreted Lady or one that giueth light &amp;c. Iſidorus Hiſpal. de vita vel obitu Sanct. c. <hi>48.</hi>
                     </note> Ladie ſtil'd, ſince by that Sonne</l>
                  <l>Thou<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Power is giuen to her both in heaven and earth, which power is, to be able to helpe vs. S. Bernard, ſerm. <hi>1.</hi> in Salue Regina.</note> both in heauen and earth art powerfull made</l>
                  <l>To eaſe their paines, who shall require thy ayde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Help me ô then ſinn's dang'rous shelues to ſhunne,</l>
                  <l>Giue me a feeling of my Sauiour's paynes,</l>
                  <l>And let me be of thoſe, whome thou retaines.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:4919:4"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 2. SANCTA DEI GENITRIX.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MOTHER OF GOD: ô rare prerogatiue!</l>
                  <l>O glorious title! what more ſpeciall grace</l>
                  <l>Could vnto thee thy deare ſonne dread God giue</l>
                  <l>To shew how farre thou doſt<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Marie by the dignitie of her election tranſcends all hight of a choſen creature. Greg. c. <hi>1.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> reg. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Mary excelled all women in vertue. Iuſtin. queſt. <hi>156.</hi>
                     </note> all creatures paſſe?</l>
                  <l>That<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Who hath ſeene? Who hath heard the like? God, who cannot be contayned in a place, dwels in a wombe: whom the heauens doe not receave, a Virgin's wombe comprehends. Proclus Conſtantinop. de nas. Chriſti, the was truly bleſſed, who was greater then heauen, ſtronger then the earth, wider then the world. For she alone compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended God, whom the world containeth not. &amp;c. Petrus Chryſol. ſer. <hi>143.</hi>
                     </note> mightie Power with in the narrow folde</l>
                  <l>Did of thy ne're polluted wombe remaine,</l>
                  <l>Whom, whiles he doth th' all ruling ſcepter holde,</l>
                  <l>Nor earth nor yet the heauens can contayne.</l>
                  <l>Thou in the ſpring-tyde of thy age brought'ſt forth</l>
                  <l>Him, (d) who before all Matter, Time, and Place,</l>
                  <l>Begotten of th' eternall Father was.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O be thou then, whyle we admire thy worth,</l>
                  <l>A meanes vnto that Sonne not to proceede</l>
                  <l>In rigour with vs for each ſinnefull deede.</l>
               </lg>
               <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Holie Marie <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (the mother of God) who holds not ſo, is an heretike. Concii. Calced. Act. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:4919:4"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 3. SANCTA VIRGO VIRGINVM.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VIRGIN OF VIRGINS, thou the<note n="(a)" place="bottom">It was by a diuine guift giuen to our Ladie, that she the firſt amongſt women should offer vp to God the glorious preſent of Virginitie Bed. ad Euangel. in Annunc. Marie The ſame is confirmed by S. Ildef. ſer. <hi>5.</hi> de Aſſumptione Marie Beda. l. <hi>1.</hi> in Luc. c. <hi>3.</hi> Hono. l. de eternis gaud. Ruſt. <hi>3.</hi> in Cant.</note> firſt did'ſt make</l>
                  <l>The ſacred vowe of ſpottles chaſtitie,</l>
                  <l>Through which example manie now forſake</l>
                  <l>The vaine world's frayle delights to follow thee.</l>
                  <l>In the whole courſe of thy liues bleſſed race,</l>
                  <l>All the perfections of<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Let the Virginitie and life of Marie be as in a picture deſcribed to you, from whome as in a looking glaſſe the beautie of Chaſtitie and forme of vertue doe yeeld a glorious reflection. Ambr. l. <hi>2.</hi> de Virg.</note> virginitie,</l>
                  <l>As in a fayre vnblemiſh'd looking-glaſſe,</l>
                  <l>In their true coulours well reflected be.</l>
                  <l>Yet, though a Virgin, thou a Mother waſt,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe fruitfull mayden wombe ſent forth a ray</l>
                  <l>Of heauenlie beames, which all Hell's errours chas'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Daigne, Virgin-Mother, to thy Sonne to pray,</l>
                  <l>That he would grant, thy great Integritie</l>
                  <l>May be a ſalue for our Impuritie.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:4919:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 4. MATER CHRISTI.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MOTHER OF CHRIST; thy vertuous life deſeru'd</l>
                  <l>That light through thee should to vs all appeare,</l>
                  <l>And that thou ſhouldſt before all others beare,</l>
                  <l>Him, who by death from death our ſoules preſeru'd.</l>
                  <l>CHRIST is the oyle powr'd out, whereby we liue,</l>
                  <l>Which yeelds vs light our grieuous faults to ſee,</l>
                  <l>Which cures our ſinnefull ſoules, and ſetts vs free</l>
                  <l>From Hell's dread paines, &amp; doth new forces giue.</l>
                  <l>In thee, Chaſte Mother, this moſt ſacred, pure,</l>
                  <l>And ſoueraigne oyle, this pretious ſalue, did growe,</l>
                  <l>And from thee to all ſinne-ſicke mortalls flowe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Requeſt of him our ſpirituall wounds to cure,</l>
                  <l>To feed our hungry ſoules, and foot-ſteps guide,</l>
                  <l>That from his bleſſed wayes, we ne're may ſlide.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:4919:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 5. MATER DIVINAE GRATIAE.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MOTHER OF DIVINE GRACE we iuſtly may</l>
                  <l>Stile thee, moſt gratious Ladie, ſince within</l>
                  <l>Thy heauen-like womb free from all guilt of ſinne</l>
                  <l>The great Diſpenſer of all Graces<note n="(a)" place="bottom">In that Virgin the treaſure of all Grace was layd. &amp;c. Greg. Neoceſar.</note> lay.</l>
                  <l>Graces chief treaſure reſted in thy hart,</l>
                  <l>What s'ere thou didſt, was<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Whatſoeuer was done in her, was all puritie and ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, all grace and truth, all mercie &amp; iuſtice, which looked downe from heauen. Sophronius. ſer. de Aſſumpt. Maria apud Hieronymum.</note> wholy Puritie,</l>
                  <l>Truth, Mercie, Iuſtice:<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Grace is giuen to others but by (certain) portions, but in Marie the whole plenitude of Grace infuſed itſelf all at once. ibid.</note> only vnto thee</l>
                  <l>Full grace was giuen, t' others but in part.</l>
                  <l>From thy deare Sonne, by thee vnto vs all,</l>
                  <l>When for ſuch guifts we doe our ſoules prepare,</l>
                  <l>All graces dayly diſtributed are.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then let vs ſtill, when s'ere we humbly call,</l>
                  <l>Be by thee heard; n'ere let vs pray in vaine,</l>
                  <l>But, when we aske for Grace, ſtill Grace obtaine.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:4919:6"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 6. MATER PVRISSIMA.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MOTHER MOST PVRE: thou pure from any shewe</l>
                  <l>Did'ſt euer liue of any ſinnefull ſtaine;</l>
                  <l>Gainſt all th' aſſaults of our accurſed foe</l>
                  <l>Thy verie<note n="(a)" place="bottom">The mother of God was not ſo much as defiled at anie time with filthie thoughts. Elias Creten. in orat <hi>4.</hi> Nazianz.</note> thoughts did victorious ſtill remaine.</l>
                  <l>From actuall ſinnes and from Originall,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſoule alone, except thy Sonne's, was free;</l>
                  <l>Yea the profoundeſt Doctours, when they fall</l>
                  <l>To ſpeake of ſinne, refuſe to mention thee.</l>
                  <l>Thy ſoule and bodie now reioyn'd do<note n="(b)" place="bottom">When we ſpeake of ſinnes, we will not, for the honour of our Lord haue any queſtion of Mary &amp;c. Aug. de na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura &amp; Gr. c. <hi>66.</hi>
                     </note> shine,</l>
                  <l>Next to thy greater Sonne, and much more pure</l>
                  <l>Then Cherubins or other powers diuine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Endeauour, pureſt Mother, to procure,</l>
                  <l>That, when our ſoules with ſinnes we tainte, we may</l>
                  <l>With flouds of teares wash all ſuch ſpottes away.</l>
               </lg>
               <note n="(c)" place="bottom">All Chriſtendome knowes that Marie is exalted aboue all the heauens, and aſſuredly beleeues, that she is placed aboue the Quires of Angels. Anſel. de excell. Mari &amp; Virg. c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:4919:6"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 7. MATER CASTISSIMA.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MOTHER MOST CHAST thou art; for thou alone</l>
                  <l>Of all thy ſex a virgin<note n="(a)" place="bottom">She conceaued a Virgin, she brought forth (her child) a Virgin. Leo magn. ſer. de Nat. Domini. c. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> didſt conceaue,</l>
                  <l>A pure chaſt Virgin broughteſt forth thy ſonne,</l>
                  <l>A Virgin alſo this frayle world didſt leaue.</l>
                  <l>Thou<note n="(b)" place="bottom">After that Mary once conceaued and brought forth her child, she neuer bore any more, neither knewe she man, though ſome doting fellowes are not afrayd to ſay, that the Virgin hirſelf conceaued an other child &amp;c. Athan. ſer. in deſcriptione S. Mar. &amp; Ioſeph. item. Cyrill. Alexand. l. <hi>2.</hi> de recta fide ad reginas. Ambr. de virginitate inſtitut. c. <hi>5.</hi> Hiero. ad c. <hi>44.</hi> Ezech. with many more &amp;c.</note> neuer didſt (let Hell ſtorme, shift, and lye)</l>
                  <l>After thy firſt-borne child a ſecond beare;</l>
                  <l>Thou ſtill wert<note n="(c)" place="bottom">The Virgin-Mother of God, purer then the beames and brightnes of the ſunne. Ephr. orat. de laud. ſant. Dei matris.</note> clearer then the world's bright eye,</l>
                  <l>Or all the lights which turne on euerie ſpheare.</l>
                  <l>Thy chaſtitie's ſtrong bands no ſtrength could cutt;</l>
                  <l>Thou art the gate through which but Iſrael's God</l>
                  <l>Doth come and goe, yet ſtill remaineth shutt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Vouchſafe, chaſte Mother, to diuert the rod</l>
                  <l>Of god's iuſt iudgements from vs, when we be</l>
                  <l>S<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>outhfull to imitate thy chaſtitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <note n="(d)" place="bottom">This is the cloſed Oriental gate, through which the Bishop alone comes in and goes out, yet it ſtill remayneth shutt. Hiero. ad c. <hi>44.</hi> Ezech.</note>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:4919:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 8. MATER INVIOLATA.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MOTHER INVIOLATED;<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Origen writes in this ſort in his Homilie <hi>1.</hi> in diuerſos.</note> who can be</l>
                  <l>A perfect mother, and yet vndefil'd?</l>
                  <l>Did euer any aged woman ſee</l>
                  <l>A maide at once and mother of a child?</l>
                  <l>None but thy ſelfe, great Mother, thou alone</l>
                  <l>Of all thy ſex this title canſt receaue;</l>
                  <l>Thou only free from all<note n="(b)" place="bottom">What is more chaſte then she, who hath brought forth a bodie without pollution of bodie? Ambr. l. <hi>2.</hi> de Virginibus,</note> contagion</l>
                  <l>Of bodie's touch, a bodie didſt conceaue.</l>
                  <l>Thy ſpotles<note n="(c)" place="bottom">The ſame is both a Mother and a Virgin, neither did her Virginitie take away the child-birth, nor the child-birth diſſolue her Virginitie. Greg. Nyſſen. <hi>2.</hi> in nat. Chriſti.</note> chaſtitie did not impeach</l>
                  <l>Thy wondrous child-birth, nor that birth againe</l>
                  <l>Make in thy Virgin's fortreſſe any breach.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Pray, we beſeech thee, that we may refraine</l>
                  <l>From each laſciuious, fond, impure deſire,</l>
                  <l>And to thy puritie in part aſpire.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:4919:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 9. MATER INTEMERATA.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MOTHER VNSPOTTED, thou art Moyſe's<note n="(a)" place="bottom">As in time paſt the bush &amp;c. and as the <hi>3.</hi> Children &amp;c. or as to Daniel &amp;c. So did this Virgin alſo bring forth God, yet remained vntouched &amp;c. Origen. Hom. in diuerſos. Exod. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> bush</l>
                  <l>Which flam'd indeede, but was not burn'd at all;</l>
                  <l>Thou art that woman, whoſe bleſt ſeede ſhould <note n="(b)" place="bottom">By thee, o more then bleſſed Virgin Marie, the diuel is ouercome and troden downe, becauſe it is written of thee; she shall bruſe thy head. Idiot. contempl. de B. Mar. c. <hi>4.</hi> item Geneſis. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> crush</l>
                  <l>The ſerpent's head, for to repaire our fall.</l>
                  <l>As in hote fornace Iſrael's three<note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Daniel.</hi> 3.</note> yong-men</l>
                  <l>Th' Almighties prayſes did vntouched ſing;</l>
                  <l>And as<note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Daniel.</hi> 14.</note> to Daniel in the lyon's den,</l>
                  <l>The doore ſhutt Abacuc did victuals bring:</l>
                  <l>So to redeeme the forfait of the tree,</l>
                  <l>Thy virgin-wombe true God true Man did beare</l>
                  <l>Without all touch vnto thy chaſtitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Grant that we may, ô ſpotles Mother, feare</l>
                  <l>To come before thee with a ſpotted, foule,</l>
                  <l>A ſinne-infected, vnprepared ſoule.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:4919:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 10. MATER AMABILIS.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>AMIABLE MOTHER, Louelie, chaſt, and<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Thou art all faire, ô my friend, and no ſpot is in thee. Cant. <hi>4.7.</hi>
                     </note> faire</l>
                  <l>Faire through the beautie of that ſpeciall grace,</l>
                  <l>And thoſe rare vertues, which without compare</l>
                  <l>Thy bounteous Sonne in thy bleſt ſoule did place.</l>
                  <l>Faire through thy ſpotles pure<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Thou art all faire in thy Conception made onely to this end, that thou mighteſt be the temple of the higheſt God. Idiot. contempl. de B. V. c. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> Conception,</l>
                  <l>Made for the temple of Heauens ſoueraigne Lord,</l>
                  <l>Faire through the wondrous Generation</l>
                  <l>Of th' Father's glorie, the Eternall Word.</l>
                  <l>Theſe and thy other graces do inflame</l>
                  <l>Each vertuous hart ſo with thy ſacred loue,</l>
                  <l>As all praiſe honour, and reſpect thy name.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let vs not then, ſweet Mother, backward proue,</l>
                  <l>While in this wretched vale of teares we liue,</l>
                  <l>To yeald thee that, which all the world doth giue.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:4919:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 11. MATER ADMIRABILIS.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ADMIRABLE MOTHER,<note n="(a)" place="bottom">This Virgin is truly the great wonder of the world. Chryſ. hom. in Hypopauten Domini.</note> wonder of the earth,</l>
                  <l>Wondrous in thy admir'd Conception,</l>
                  <l>Wondrous alike in thy moſt bleſſed Birth,</l>
                  <l>Thy courſe of life, death, and Aſſumption.</l>
                  <l>What is more wondrous then that thou a mayde</l>
                  <l>Didſt beare a childe, and yet a mayde remain'dſt?</l>
                  <l>Is ought more ſtrange then that it may be ſaide:</l>
                  <l>Thou him,<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Thou art the circumſcription (that I may ſo ſay) of him, who cannot be circumſcribed &amp;c. Thou art the compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion (or conteyner) of him, who containes and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends all things. Methodius Tyri Epiſcop. orat. in Hypag. Domini.</note> whom nought could circumſcribe, contain'dſt?</l>
                  <l>All thy diſcourſes, nay each very thought,</l>
                  <l>Much more thy deeds, moſt rare and wondrous were,</l>
                  <l>And farre aboue our common merits wrought.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Grant that thy wondrous vertues may appeare</l>
                  <l>So liuely to our minds, that when we neede,</l>
                  <l>We, how to liue, in them may patterns reade.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:4919:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 12. MATER CREATORIS.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MOTHER OF OVR CREATOVR; he, who firſt</l>
                  <l>Did build the houſe, himſelf was borne therein;</l>
                  <l>Thy pureſt<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Only Chriſt did open the cloſed gate of the Virginall wombe; which notwithſtanding allwayes remayned shutt &amp;c. Hier. l. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> aduerſ. Pelagianos c. <hi>2.</hi> item Ruffin. in expl. Symb. &amp; alij.</note> wombe without a breach he pearc't,</l>
                  <l>By whom thou hadſt before created beene.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He, who fills all things, to whoſe powerfull might</l>
                  <l>All creatures bowe, thy help oftimes<note n="(b)" place="bottom">He who fills heauen &amp; earth, is become needie of thee. Method. or. in Hypag. Domini.</note> receau'd:</l>
                  <l>Thou that GREAT-ONE, great Mother, broughtſt to light,</l>
                  <l>Who<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Thou in the end of times broughteſt forth him, who was conceaued before all ages. ibid.</note> long before all ages was conceau'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>At thy moſt chaſte Annunciation,</l>
                  <l>Thou, what he had not, vnto him didſt giue,</l>
                  <l>Who nothing wants: his Incarnation.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Grant that we may, not only while we liue,</l>
                  <l>But alſo at our death, partakers be</l>
                  <l>Of the bleſt fruit of this great myſterie.</l>
               </lg>
               <note n="(d)" place="bottom">Thou didſt lend to God his admirable Incarnation, which ſometime he had not. ibid.</note>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:4919:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 13. MATER SALVATORIS.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MOTHER OF OVR SAVIOVR; thou before all others</l>
                  <l>Waſt choſen t' beare the ranſome of vs all;</l>
                  <l>For which all Nations farre aboue all<note n="[a)" place="bottom">Thou art truly bleſſed who alone amongſt all Mothers, waſt choſen to be Mother to thy Creatour. Andr. Cret. orat. in Ann. B. Virg.</note> Mothers</l>
                  <l>That euer were, thee euer bleſſed call.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Th'<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Thou did'ſt diſcloſe to the world the Sonne of the inuiſible Father, by whom all peace is reſtored to vs: a hidden ſuretie, &amp; an ineffable myſterie. Method. Epiſc. Tyri. or. in Hyp.</note> eternall Fathers Sonne, by whom we ſee</l>
                  <l>Our ancient foe's malicious ſpleene repreſt,</l>
                  <l>That hidden, ſacred, wondrous myſterie,</l>
                  <l>To wretched mortals thou didſt manifeſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou art that glorious<note n="(c)" place="bottom">O bleſſed virgin thou art a bright clowd, which brought from heauen that moſt cleare lightning, Chriſt to illuminate the world &amp;c. Epiph. ſerm. de Laud. B. V.</note> clowd, from whence did flye</l>
                  <l>That radiant lightning, whoſe reſplendent rayes</l>
                  <l>Clear'd all the world, which did in darknes lye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Be thou a meanes, bleſſed Mother, when we praiſe</l>
                  <l>Thy heauenly vertues, we may vices hate,</l>
                  <l>And thy perfections truly imitate.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:4919:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 14. VIRGO PRVDENTISSIMA.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VIRGIN MOST WISE thou rightly maiſt be ſtil'd,</l>
                  <l>Since thy rare wiſedome did anticipate</l>
                  <l>So farre thy yeares, as yet a tender child,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſelf to God thou diddeſt conſecrate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou, to thy wiſdome's neuer dying praiſe</l>
                  <l>T'reach the Conception<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Is not Mary a high mountaine, who to the end shee might reach the Conception of the Eternall Word, raiſed vp the topp of her merits aboue all quyers of Angels, euen to the throne of the Deitie. Greg. mag. l. <hi>1.</hi> Reg. c. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> of th' Eternal's Sonne</l>
                  <l>Did'ſt the high mountaine of thy merits rayſe</l>
                  <l>Aboue all Saints, euen to th' Almighties throne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Where like<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Eſther. c. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </note> a prudent Heſter without ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>Thou doſt before thy ſweet Sonne humbly pray</l>
                  <l>For our poore ſinn-enthralled ſoul's releaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Obtaine, moſt prudent Virgin, that we may</l>
                  <l>Prepare our ſelues a right, to taſt the fruit</l>
                  <l>Of this thy, till th' world end, nere ended ſuite.</l>
               </lg>
               <note n="(a)" place="bottom">libr. de ortu Virg. apud Hieronymum.</note>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:4919:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 15. VIRGO VENERANDA.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VIRGIN MOST VENERABLE, thy Royall race,</l>
                  <l>Thy vertuous life, and now immortall rayes,</l>
                  <l>Deſerue farre better, then all humane race,</l>
                  <l>Ciuill, Religious, and Coeleſtiall prayſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou art the<note n="(a)" place="bottom">This alone is the bridge, by which God deſcended to man, Prod. Conſtantinop. hom. de Nat. Chriſti.</note> bridge, by which God came to man;</l>
                  <l>Thou art the ſecond Adam's<note n="(b)" place="bottom">This is the ſpirituall paradiſe of the ſecond Adam. ibid.</note> paradiſe;</l>
                  <l>To thee (ſo high a place thy merits wann)</l>
                  <l>Next<note n="(c)" place="bottom">For, God only excepted, thou art aboue all. Epiph. ſerm. de laud. B. V.</note> vnto God, chiefe honour doth ariſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who but an Atheiſt will refuſe to ſerue</l>
                  <l>So great a Miſtreſſe? who doth euery way</l>
                  <l>Such ſupreme honour worthily deſerue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O let vs then, great Virgin, while we ſtay</l>
                  <l>In this frayle world, thy humble agents be,</l>
                  <l>To moue thy greateſt foes to honour thee.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:4919:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 16. VIRGO PRAEDICANDA.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VIRGIN MOST WORTHIE PRAISE, by much more great</l>
                  <l>Then<note n="(a)" place="bottom">A heauenlie and earthlie tongue, no nor the tongue of Angels, can ſuffiſe to rehearſe thy praiſes. Epiph. Serm. de laud. B. V.</note> men, then Saints, or Angels can explaine:</l>
                  <l>For in thy bleſſed wombe he fix't his ſeat</l>
                  <l>Whom all the earth's huge maſt cannot ſuſtaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou the Mediatrix<note n="(b)" place="bottom">For she is the Mediatrix of heauen and earth, who natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally accomplished the vnion. ibid.</note> art twixt God and man;</l>
                  <l>By thee whole Nations<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Through Marie Nations are brought to pennance. Cyrill. Alex. hom. Epheſ. in Neſtor. habita.</note> are to pennance brought;</l>
                  <l>The All-creatour firſt with thee beganne,</l>
                  <l>When he the world's deſir'd Saluation wrought.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou th' interpoſed<note n="(d)" place="bottom">Hayle thou who paſsing as Mediatrix betwixt God and Man, procureſt that the interpoſed wall of enmitus may at length be ouerthrowne, &amp; earthly things ioyned to Celeſtiall. Baſil. Selutius, or. in Annun. Dei.</note> wall of hate did'ſt raiſe</l>
                  <l>Twixt God &amp; man; thou heauen ioyn'dſt to earth;</l>
                  <l>What can be greater? what more worthie praiſe?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Aske thy deare Sonne, we may eu'n from our birth</l>
                  <l>(Through theſe and all thy merits) ere we dye</l>
                  <l>For all our ſinfull courſes ſatisfye.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:4919:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 17. VIRGO POTENS.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VIRGIN MOST POTENT: from that powerfull Lord,</l>
                  <l>Whom dwelling<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Shé vpon earth conceiued God dwelling in heauen. Epiph. ſerm. de laudibus. B. V.</note> high in heauen thou didſt conceaue</l>
                  <l>Low vpon earth, thou ſtill doſt power<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Vid. Sancta Maria. at<note n="(c)" place="bottom">By whom Diuells are put to flight, by whom the Diuell tempter fell from heauen, and by whome all creatures poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with the rage of Idolls, are brought to the knowledge of the truth, &amp;c. Cyr. Alex. hom. Epheſ in Heſt.</note>
                     </note> receaue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>To all, that craue thy ayde, thy ayde t' afford.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Through thee th'Infernal<note n="(c)" place="bottom">By whom Diuells are put to flight, by whom the Diuell tempter fell from heauen, and by whome all creatures poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with the rage of Idolls, are brought to the knowledge of the truth, &amp;c. Cyr. Alex. hom. Epheſ in Heſt.</note> troupes are put to flight;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Through thee curſt Sathan did from heauen fall;</l>
                  <l>Through thee all thoſe, who nought adored at all</l>
                  <l>But ſenſeles Idols, now belieue a right.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By thee thy Seruants well rewarded are,</l>
                  <l>And alſo diuers, who thy power<note n="(d)" place="bottom">Daureltius tom. <hi>21.</hi> Exemplerum tit. <hi>68.</hi>
                     </note> deride,</l>
                  <l>Receiue by thee due payment for their pride.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Grant we may haue, great Virgin, ſtill a care</l>
                  <l>To feare and reuerence thy moſt powerfull name,</l>
                  <l>And ſtriue in others to effect the ſame.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:4919:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 18. VIRGO CLEMENS.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VIRGIN MOST MERCIFVLL, moſt milde, and meeke;</l>
                  <l>The ioy of euerie well-affected minde</l>
                  <l>What ſinner e're to thee did humbly<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Thou art the help of thoſe, who ſinne &amp; who are deſtitute of ayde: thou art the hauen of them who are troubled with a ſtorme, the comfort of the world, &amp; the hope of ſuch as liue in the world. Coſ. Ephr. orat. de laud. B. V.</note> ſeeke</l>
                  <l>Who thy aſſiſtance did not readie find?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Thou art the help of thoſe, who ſinne &amp; who are deſtitute of ayde: thou art the hauen of them who are troubled with a ſtorme, the comfort of the world, &amp; the hope of ſuch as liue in the world. Coſ. Ephr. orat. de laud. B. V.</note> art the hope and comfort of vs all;</l>
                  <l>Thou art a quiet hauen shut to none;</l>
                  <l>To ſuch, as penitent for mercy call,</l>
                  <l>Thou<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Reioyce o diuine refuge of reconciliation betwixt God and men. And. Cret. orat. in Annunt. B. V.</note> by thy prayers doſt reconcile thy Sonne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thee<note n="(c)" place="bottom">The world hath made thee the pledge of their faith with God. Ceſ. Auguſt. de SS. ſerm. <hi>18.</hi>
                     </note> the whole world with vniforme conſent,</l>
                  <l>The pledge with God of their true faith hath made;</l>
                  <l>Nor doth thy fauour fruſtrate their intent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Mercifull Virgin, let it not be ſaid,</l>
                  <l>That only we miſſe that, which all men haue,</l>
                  <l>But<note n="(d)" place="bottom">Repreſſe, O B. Virgin, my temptations, order my life after a pious and holie manner, and cauſe that by thy directions, I may attaine to heauenlie beatitude. Io. Damaſc. or. <hi>1.</hi> de Nat. Mari.</note> guide our ſtepps, and foules vouchſafe to ſaue.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:4919:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 19. VIRGO FIDELIS.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VIRGIN MOST FAITHFVLL: in that vertue none</l>
                  <l>Could euer neere be paralell'd with thee.</l>
                  <l>Faithfull thou wert in that from perils free</l>
                  <l>Thou ſtill preſeru'dſt thine, and th' Almightie's Sonne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When at his paſſion he was left alone,</l>
                  <l>Thou faithfull follow'dſt to th' erected tree;</l>
                  <l>Who askt' thee ere his Patroneſſe<note n="(b)" place="bottom">who hath, ô Lady, hoped in thee, and was after asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med? or what man hath faithfully implored thy almightie help and was euer forſaken. Surely neuer any. Eutychia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus in vita S. Theophili.</note> to be,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe wishes thou did'ſt fruſtrate? ſurely none.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou ſtill art true, ſtill faithfull vnto all,</l>
                  <l>Who faithfull aske thy aide; and oft preuents</l>
                  <l>The foe's deceipts, which may our ſoules enthrall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Second then our good and iuſt intents.</l>
                  <l>Direct our actions all, and doe not faile.</l>
                  <l>To<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Defend me, &amp; from the eternall fire and darknes free me. Greg. Naz. in Tragedia.</note> guarde vs, leaſt againſt vs Hell preuaile.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:4919:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 20. SPECVLVM IVSTITIAE.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LOOkING-GLASSE OF IVSTICE: he who would</l>
                  <l>Forſaking vice a vertuous courſe embrace,</l>
                  <l>May in thy<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Such an one was Marie, that the life of her alone is the inſtruction of all men. Ambr. de Virgin. vide etiam de hacre S. Virgo Virg.</note> life, as in a ſpotles glaſſe,</l>
                  <l>The perfect ſhape of vertues all behold.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou art the<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Reioyce o mirrour, through which they, who were in the thick shades of ſinne, receiuing the ſunne of Iuſtice coming from heauen, were enlightened, And. Cret. or. in Annunc. B. V.</note> glaſſe, through whoſe pure chriſtall came</l>
                  <l>The glorious Sunne of Iuſtice from the Skye,</l>
                  <l>T' enlighten thoſe who in ſinne's ſhades did lye,</l>
                  <l>And with his rayes their frozen harts inflame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No pale infernall ſpleene, though it repine</l>
                  <l>To ſee thy luſter, can impoſe one ſtaine</l>
                  <l>On thy pure ſplendour, but thy beames will shine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O let vs ſtill before this glaſſe remaine;</l>
                  <l>That, when we riſe from ſinn's dull ſleep, we may</l>
                  <l>Learne our naked ſoules with vertues to array.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:4919:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 21. SEDES SAPIENTIAE.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>O SEAT OF WISEDOME: heauen's ſupreme Lord,</l>
                  <l>Th' eternall's Wiſedome, he who did beget</l>
                  <l>All things of nothing, only by his word,</l>
                  <l>Eſteem'd thee<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Marie is a glorified Seate &amp; worthie of God, which can by only the eyes of the minde be ſeene. Meth. in Threnis.</note> worthie t' be his ſacred ſeate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That heauenlie<note n="(b)" place="bottom">In whom be all the treaſures of wiſedome and knowledge hid. Coloſſ <hi>2.3.</hi>
                     </note> treaſure, where all treaſures lye</l>
                  <l>Of God's high wiſedome, in thee ſeated was;</l>
                  <l>In thee he did our fraile humanitie</l>
                  <l>Eſpouſe,<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Reioyce, o bed chamber, in which Chriſt eſpouſed humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. And. Cret. or. Ann. B. V.</note> not preſſ'd through<note n="(d)" place="bottom">Marie excelled euery one ſo much that she receiued God himſelf the Word (very willing to be receiued) whom she comprehended citra vllam loci anguſtiam. Without any ſtraitneſſe of place. Heſychius Hieroſol. or. <hi>1.</hi> de Sancta Maria Deipara.</note> ſtraitnes of the place.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Beſides thou maiſt be called Wiſedome's ſeate,</l>
                  <l>In that great wiſedomes euer flowing Well,</l>
                  <l>In ſtreames of grace, into thy Soule ſtill fell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O doe thy Sonne (Wiſedome's great throne) intreat</l>
                  <l>That he would pleaſe ſometimes to be our gueſt,</l>
                  <l>And ſometimes in our craſie Soules to reſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:4919:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 22. CAVSA NOSTRAE LAETITIAE.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>CAVSE OF OVR IOY: th' Serpent<note n="(a)" place="bottom">The Serpent ſeduced Eue, Marie conſented to Gabriel, but the ſeducing of Eue brought death, the conſent of Mary brought life. Ioannes Chryſ. ſer. de Gen &amp; interdict. ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor. ad Adam. item: Life was reſtored by Mary, which had beene ſlaine by Eue. <hi>16.</hi>
                     </note> did Eue ſeduce;</l>
                  <l>Thou vnto Gabriel humbly gau'ſt conſent;</l>
                  <l>But Eue's ſeducing, death and diſcord, ſent;</l>
                  <l>Thy prompt obedience, life, and ſetled truce.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>She made vs<note n="(b)" place="bottom">The mother of our kind brought paine into the world, the Mother of our Lord brought to the world health. Eue the authour of ſinne, Mary the author of merit. Aug. de Sanctif. ſerm. <hi>18.</hi>
                     </note> ſick; thou brought vs preſent health;</l>
                  <l>She ſinne, thou merit, to the world did'ſt bring.</l>
                  <l>She made vs weepe, thou gau'ſt vs cauſe to ſing:</l>
                  <l>Our ſoules she rob'd but thou increas'd our wealth</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In brief, thou art that inſtrument<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Reioyce, ô inſtrument of ioy, by which the ſad Sentence of execration is changed into the pleaſant iudgment of ioy. And. Cret. or. in Annun. B. V.</note> of ioy,</l>
                  <l>Which Eue's ſad curſes did to bleſſings turne,</l>
                  <l>And makeſt vs (if we will) we ne're neede mourne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Help vs, we may our talents ſo employ,</l>
                  <l>That, when we doe this houſe of cares forſake,</l>
                  <l>We may with thee of heauenly ioyes partake.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:4919:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 23. VAS SPIRITVALE,</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SPIRITVALL VESSELL; thou did'ſt ſo containe</l>
                  <l>All ſpirituall riches of celeſtiall grace,</l>
                  <l>That to the height of thy moſt glorious place</l>
                  <l>None of thy ſex ere could, e're can, attaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy veſſell's beautie thou did'ſt n'ere deface</l>
                  <l>With any ſinfull death-importing ſtaine;</l>
                  <l>But ſtill thy heauenlie luſtre did'ſt retaine</l>
                  <l>And all foule ſoule-deforming vices chaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Which to effect thou did'ſt more grace obtaine,</l>
                  <l>In that thou wa'ſt to beare ſo long a ſpace</l>
                  <l>The ſole procurer of our ſpirituall gaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Graunt we may ſtill (ô ſpirituall veſſel) trace</l>
                  <l>Thy ſpotles pathes and neuer ſtriue in vaine</l>
                  <l>From th' impure ſtench of loathſome ſinne t' refraine.</l>
               </lg>
               <note n="(a)" place="bottom">No woman euer did, not euer shall obtaine ſo much grace as the Mother of our Lord. Tit. Boſtreuſis ad c. <hi>1.</hi> Luc.</note>
               <note n="(b)" place="bottom">There was neuer any filth, vice, or ſinne in thy glorious ſoule.</note>
               <note n="[c]" place="bottom">Marie receiued more grace vtterly to ouerthrow Sinne, who deſerued to conceiue &amp; bring forth him, who it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent had no ſinne. Aug. de nat. &amp; grat. c. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:4919:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 24. VAS HONORABILE.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HONORABLE VESSELL which th'eternall word</l>
                  <l>Did for his owne, beſt ſeruice only frame,</l>
                  <l>And vnto thee on eu'ry syde afforde</l>
                  <l>The glittering<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Hayle ô cleare and beautifull veſſell of God. Ephraem orat. de laud. Deiparae.</note> luſter of a heauenly flame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou art that pretious veſſell which to man</l>
                  <l>Did from the skye life-giuing MANNA beare,</l>
                  <l>In thee th' Allmighty's mighty ſonne began</l>
                  <l>A health to all, who doe his dread name feare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou art that honour'd veſſell which<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Hayle thou who art a pitt of euer liuing water. Chryſip. presb. de laud. <hi>v.</hi> Maria.</note> contain'd</l>
                  <l>Th' water of life; in thee that powerfull One,</l>
                  <l>Which all thinges fills, whole &amp; intyre remain'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Help vs to be (moſt honour'd veſſell) prone</l>
                  <l>To vertue euer vnto vices ſlowe,</l>
                  <l>And perfectly our imperfections knowe.</l>
               </lg>
               <note n="(b)" place="bottom">Hayle full of grace which art a goulden veſſell contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning heauenly Manna. Epipha. Ser. de laud. Deip.</note>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:4919:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 25. VAS INSIGNE DEVOTIONIS.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>RENOWNED VESSELL OF DEVOTION</l>
                  <l>Fountaine<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Thou art truely the moſt copious well of all Sanctity &amp;c. Method. orat in Hyp. din.</note> of Sanctity which euermore</l>
                  <l>With ne're decreaſing Springes of grace doſt runne</l>
                  <l>Weake ſoules to wonted vigour to reſtore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy great CREATOR by<note n="(b)" place="bottom">That moſt gratious Creator did throwe into the flames of moſt feruent Charity like certaine thicke heapd beames of the ſunne <hi>16.</hi>
                     </note> abundant ſtreames</l>
                  <l>With out reſtraint infuſed into thee</l>
                  <l>Like to the glorious Sunn's cleare-shining beames,</l>
                  <l>Deuouteſt flames of feruent Charity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whoſe neuer-quenched heate, diſperſed ſtill</l>
                  <l>Among'ſt vs, doth our froſen harts inflame,</l>
                  <l>And our cold breſt with true deuotion fill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our dayly actions (ſacred veſſell) frame</l>
                  <l>So that wee may deſeruedly aſpire,</l>
                  <l>To gaine but one ſparke of ſo great a fyer.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:4919:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 26. ROSA MYSTICA.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MYSTICALL ROSE, diuinely white &amp; red,</l>
                  <l>Whyte through the Candour of virginity</l>
                  <l>Red through the heate of burning charity</l>
                  <l>Whyte in thy ſpotleſſe flesh, in mind ſtill red.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In following vertue's pure directiones, white;</l>
                  <l>Red by thy trampling vpon vices head;</l>
                  <l>Through the care thou haſt of our good courſes, red;</l>
                  <l>And by thy loue to thy Creator, white.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou from the Iewes, as from sharpe thornes, didſt riſe</l>
                  <l>And through the word all banefull fumes expell,</l>
                  <l>By thy rare vertues euer fragrant ſmell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Driue from our ſoules th' infectious ſtench of vice</l>
                  <l>That wee before thy ſonne may without feare</l>
                  <l>Perfum'd<note n="(c)" place="bottom">good perfume of Chriſt in euery place.</note> with vertues at our death appeare.</l>
               </lg>
               <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Mary was a Roſe whyte by virginity, red by charity whyte in flech, red in mind; whyte through her following of virtue, red through her trampling on vices, whyte in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying her affections, red in mortifying the carnall. Whyte in louing God, red in hauing compaſsion of her neighbour. Bernard ſer. de S. Maria.</note>
               <note n="(b)" place="bottom">Roſe, which art sprung from thornes, that is, from the Iewes, &amp; haſt filled all thinges with deuine ſweet odours. Io Damaſc. orat. <hi>1.</hi> de nat. B. V. Wee are the</note>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:4919:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 27. TVRRIS DAVIDICA.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>TOWER<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Thy necke is as the tower of Dauid, which is built with bulwarkes: a thouſand targats hang one it, all the armour of the valiant. Cant. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> OF DAVID, as that pious king</l>
                  <l>Did, for his cities ſtrength, this tower erect,</l>
                  <l>So ſpiritual DAVID thee to th' world did bring</l>
                  <l>The holy Church (his citie) to protect.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This tower prouiſion through the towne did ſpread;</l>
                  <l>By thee, according vnto Natures law</l>
                  <l>In humane bodies, wee, from Chriſt the head,</l>
                  <l>As by the necke, all ſpirituall victualls drawe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In DAVID'S tower all warlike armes were layd;</l>
                  <l>Thou ſtill art ready, as the Church'es sheed,</l>
                  <l>Our ſoules againſt all Hell's aſſaults to ayd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Helpe then ô leaſt wee vnprotected yeeld,</l>
                  <l>Succour the weake, &amp; thoſe who humbly weepe,</l>
                  <l>And flye to thee, in thy tuitions keepe.</l>
               </lg>
               <note n="(b)" place="bottom">Holy Mary ſuccour the wretched, help the faint harted, comfort thoſe who weepe, pray for the people. &amp;c. Aug. ſer. <hi>18.</hi> de Sanctis.</note>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:4919:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 28. TVRRIS EBVRNEA.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IVORIE<note n="[a)" place="bottom">Thy necke as a tower of Iuory. Cantic. c. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note> TOWER, the<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Thou therefore the noſe of the Church art like to a tower, to wit, high in dignity &amp; firme in grauity. Bern. ſup. fal. Reg.</note> place's dignity</l>
                  <l>Which thy deare Sonne did for ſole thee reſerue,</l>
                  <l>Which thy graue mind's ne're moued conſtancy,</l>
                  <l>This worthy title iuſtly doth deſerue,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou art compar'd to pureſt Iuory</l>
                  <l>In that from<note n="(c)" place="bottom">His Mother an immaculate Mother, an incorrupt Mother, an vntouched Mother &amp;c. Orig. hom. <hi>1.</hi> Diuerſos. vid. Mater puriſsima at <hi>(a) (b) (c)</hi> &amp;c. Regina confeſſorum at <hi>(6.)</hi>
                     </note> all, euen from the leaſt foule ſtaine</l>
                  <l>Of eu'ry ſort of ſinne, thou euer free</l>
                  <l>Euen from thy firſt giuen being did'ſt remaine</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Infinit valyes of Infernall shott</l>
                  <l>Hell's curſed feenes diſcharg'd againſt thy breſt,</l>
                  <l>Yet neuer hope of leaſt aduantage got.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Permit vs euer when wee are oppreſt</l>
                  <l>With fierce aſſaults of our ne're reſting foe,</l>
                  <l>That vnto thee wee may for ſuccour goe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:4919:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 29. DOMVS AVREA.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>O HOVSE OF GOVLD, as wiſeſt SALOMON</l>
                  <l>Th' Allmighty's temple did with great reſpect</l>
                  <l>Adorne with gould, ſo thy farr wiſer ſonne</l>
                  <l>With gould of vertue, thee, his<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Reioyce ô moſt beautifull temple of deuine glory. Andr. Cret. Or. in Annunc.</note> temple, deckt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou art that rare, then gould farr brighter, houſe,</l>
                  <l>Where the two<note n="(b)" place="bottom">This is the shopp where the natures were vnited. Proclus Conſt. hom. de Natiuit. Chriſti. &amp; Serg. Hierap. Or. in nat. B. V.</note> natures both vnited were,</l>
                  <l>Where our<note n="(c)" place="bottom">This is the bed-chamber in which the word eſpouſed hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane flesh. Procl. Conſt. hom. de Nat. Chriſti. &amp; Andr. Cret. Or. in Ann. B. V.</note> humanity Chriſt did eſpouſe,</l>
                  <l>And firſt beganne our miſeries to beare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou art the manſion both of heauen and earth,</l>
                  <l>Thou art<note n="(d)" place="bottom">Hayle ô liuing temple of God: Hayle ô manſion both of heauen and earth. Io. Chryſoſt. Or. in Annuc. B. V.</note> Gods liuing temple, hee who was</l>
                  <l>Before ought was, of thee receau'd his birth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Inuite my ſoule vnto this glorious place,</l>
                  <l>That there ſhe may with fruitfull wonder gaze</l>
                  <l>Vppon thy merits gould-ſurpaſſing rayes.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:4919:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 30. FAEDERIS ARCA.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ARKE OF THE COV'NANT in that (a) arke did reſt</l>
                  <l>The tables of God's holy teſtament,</l>
                  <l>In thee, a farr more bleſt, farr richer cheſt</l>
                  <l>The Teſtament's great heire was willing pent;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Within that coſtly arke the lawes repos'd,</l>
                  <l>In thee thy ſonn's heauen-giuing Ghoſpell laye,</l>
                  <l>In that was ſtill th' Aeternall voyce inclos'd,</l>
                  <l>In thee th' eternall word it ſelf did ſtay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That wood was<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Bern. ſer. de Maria.</note> incorruptible, ſo thou;</l>
                  <l>Earthly decaying gould did that adorne,</l>
                  <l>Thou did'ſt all gould, which was not heauenly. ſcorne,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Suffer<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Reioyce ô new arke of God, in which the ſpirit of God reſteth. Arke wherein Chriſt our Not kept his humanity: Andr. Cret. orat. in Annunc. B. M.</note> me then, moſt ſacred arke, to bowe</l>
                  <l>Before thee ſtill, and with ſubmiſſiue feare</l>
                  <l>Thy ſonn's will thence in all my actions heare.</l>
               </lg>
               <note place="bottom">What other thing shall we ſay the arke to be but <hi>S.</hi> Marie? For the arke carried within the tables of the teſtament, but Mary did beare the heire of the teſtament it ſelf, that held within it the law this the Goſpell: that had the voyce of God, this the word but the arke both within and without: did glitter with the brightneſſe of gold, but holy Mary shined both within &amp; without: with the glory of virginity: that was adorned with earthly gould, this with heauenly. Ambr. tom. <hi>3.</hi> ſer. <hi>80.</hi>
               </note>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:4919:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 31. IANVA CAELI.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>O GATE OF HEAVEN open vnto all,</l>
                  <l>Who with the hammer of repentance knocke;</l>
                  <l>Noe barr of malice, noe reuengfull locke</l>
                  <l>Exclude<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Vide; Virgo fidelis at (b)</note> ſuch ſoules as with ſubmiſſion call.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou art<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Reioyce ô heauen, in which the ſunne of glory shines. Andr. Cret. orat. in Ann. B. V.</note> heauen it ſelf, in thee's heauen's glorious <note n="(c)" place="bottom">Mary is made the window of heauen, becauſe through her god ſent true light to (all) ages. Fulgent. ſer. de laud. B. V.</note> gate,</l>
                  <l>Through which that powerfull all reuealing eye</l>
                  <l>Gods onely ſonne paſt, when hee came to buye</l>
                  <l>Our captiue ſoules at ſo extreame a rate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Eue<note n="(d)" place="bottom">Whence death had the beginning of her entrance thence life makes herſelf a paſſage. Chr. orat. in Annunc. B. V.</note> was the dore of death, through which to hell</l>
                  <l>Diuers haue paſs'd, thou art the<note n="(e)" place="bottom">This woman the Mother of God is the gate of life, the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of light, and diſſolues the fault of women. Damaſc. orat. <hi>1.</hi> de Nat. B. V.</note> gate of life,</l>
                  <l>By which in heauen millions now doe dwell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Help me, bleſt gate to cauſe a pious ſtrif</l>
                  <l>Here in the world, who firſt amongſt vs ſhall</l>
                  <l>At this moſt ſacred gate for entrance call.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:4919:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 32. STELLA MATVTINA.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>O MORNING STAR, when wee this ſtar behould</l>
                  <l>Wee are forewarned of th' approaching Sonne,</l>
                  <l>Thy glorious riſing to the world foretold</l>
                  <l>The comming of a brighter Sun, thy Sonne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The sky's moſt glorious ſtar cannot compare</l>
                  <l>In glitt'ring clearnes with the morning ſtar;</l>
                  <l>Al<note n="(a)" place="bottom">What is more holy then she? not the Prophets, not the Apoſtles not Martyres, not Patriarchs, not Fathers, not Angels, not Thrones, not Dominations, not Cherubins, not Seraphins to conclude not any other thing amongſt viſible or inuiſible creatures can be found more great or excellent then only shee. Io. Chryſ. Hom. in Hye. dom.</note> Angels thou and greateſt Saints that are</l>
                  <l>In glorie, worth, and place ſurpaſſeſt farre.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This ſtar, though great, ſeemes to our eyes but small</l>
                  <l>So thou with thy profound<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Behould the handmaid of our Lord, be it done to me ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy word. Luc. <hi>1.38.</hi>
                     </note> humility</l>
                  <l>Didſt couer ſtil thy glorious Sanctity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Reſt in our ſoules bright ſtar, and thither call</l>
                  <l>The Sunne of Iuſtice, that his heauenly light</l>
                  <l>May thence expell darkeſin's Infernall night.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:4919:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET.</hi> 33. SALVS INFIRMORVM.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HEALTH OF THE SICK, the impotent, and lame</l>
                  <l>Thou oft haſt heal'd, thou<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Iuſtus Lipſius in dinâ Sichamienſi, ſiue Aſpricoli impr. Antwerpia <hi>1603.</hi>
                     </note> cur'd the deaf and blind:</l>
                  <l>What infirme perſon euer humbly came</l>
                  <l>To thee for help, who did not ſuccour find?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In thy chaſt wombe th' worlds al preſeruing King?</l>
                  <l>The eternall health did of our ſoules beginne:</l>
                  <l>Thou did'ſt to all the great<note n="(b)" place="bottom">By this (Virgin) ô beloued, the phiſician comes to thoſe who are ſick. Io. Chriſoft. pr. in Annun B. V.</note> phiſitian bringe,</l>
                  <l>Who cures the world from leproſies of ſinne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou by the vertue of that ſoueraigne fruit</l>
                  <l>Which thou brought'ſt forth<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Shee (Eue) gaue the blowe, this (Marie) heal'd it. Aug. de Sanctis ſer. <hi>18.</hi>
                     </note> heald'ſt vp the rankling ſoare.</l>
                  <l>Which by Eues fruit empoiſon'd was before.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Heare ô celeſtiall baulme, thy patients ſuite,</l>
                  <l>That when we ſinn-ſick are, thou would'ſt be ſure</l>
                  <l>T' entreat thy ſonne to take in hand our cure.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:4919:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 34. REFVGIVM PECCATORVM.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>REFVGE OF SINNERS, wee when e're we haue</l>
                  <l>In curre'd the iuſt diſpleaſure of thy Sonne,</l>
                  <l>To thy protection, there our ſelues to ſaue,</l>
                  <l>As to a Sacred Sanctuarie runne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou pardon beggſt,<note n="(a)" place="bottom">If a man cal vpon the name of the mother though the merits of him that cals do not deſerue that hee be heard, yet the merits of the Mother make interceſsion that he may be heard. Anſ. Cant, de excell. B. V. c. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </note> and where our merits are</l>
                  <l>Wholy defectiue, to entreat for grace,</l>
                  <l>Thou with thy owne ſupplyes thy only care</l>
                  <l>Is how from vs thou may'ſt al perils chace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou art the port, where wee may ſafely lye,</l>
                  <l>Th' ſpeedy repayrer of our wrecht eſtate,</l>
                  <l>To thee for ayd, and ſaueguard all do flye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Open, bleſt refuge, thy compaſſion's gate,</l>
                  <l>That when wee are with Hell's aſſaults oppreſt,</l>
                  <l>Wee ſafe in thee may lye, and take our reſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <note n="(b)" place="bottom">Thou art my port, o vndefiled virgin, and preſent helper, laſtly, I am wholy vnder thy cuſtodie <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and protection, Ephram. orat. de land. B. V.</note>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:4919:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 35. CONSOLATRIX AFFLICTORVM.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>O CONFORTRESSE OF AFFLICTED, thou</l>
                  <l>Send's ſpirituall<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Who is the comfort of them who are afflicted: whoe is the reuenge of them, who are troubled who is the cloathing of them which are naked Entychi de poenis. S. Theophili.</note> comfort in our miſeries,</l>
                  <l>Thou doeſt reuenge our greateſt miſeries,</l>
                  <l>And ſtil thy help on al our dangers shewe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What greater comfort can we euer haue,</l>
                  <l>Then t' thinke that when wee moſt afflicted are,</l>
                  <l>Wee haue a patroneſſe, whoſe only care</l>
                  <l>Is how shee may vs from all perils ſaue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our ſouls<note n="(b)" place="bottom">All hayle, o peace ioy: and health of the world hayle the ioye of mankind, &amp;c. Hayle the calme port and freer of them who are toſſed with waues &amp;c. Ephr. orat. de landibus B. V.</note> craysd barke thou doeſt in tempeſts guide,</l>
                  <l>Thou the diſperſer of our ſadſt annoye,</l>
                  <l>Thou art the ſickly worlds health, peace, and ioye,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When the moſt dangerous troubles wee abide</l>
                  <l>Doe not, ô do not thy beſt helpe denie,</l>
                  <l>And wee'll all Hell's moſt powerfull power defye.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:4919:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 36. AVXILIVM CHRISTIANORVM.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="(a)" place="bottom">Marye, always cherisheth Chriſtians in her armes. Eutich. de panit. Sancti. Theph.</note>SVCCOVR OF CHRISTIANS, who can e're expreſſe</l>
                  <l>The infinite<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Of all theſe ſee flores exempl. Ant. Dauroultij c. <hi>2.</hi> tit. <hi>38.39.40.41.42.</hi> &amp; <hi>43.</hi>
                     </note> helps wee all receiue from thee?</l>
                  <l>From perils oft, of war thou ſet's vs free,</l>
                  <l>And doſt the furie of our foes repreſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If e're we be in ſpirituall diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Wee by thee<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Thou art the ayde of ſinners, and of thoſe who are deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of helpe. Ephrem. or, de land. B. V.</note> help't, by thee protected bee,</l>
                  <l>Thou reconcileſt frends by thee we ſee</l>
                  <l>Diſpaire expel'd, thou doeſt our wronges redreſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>At the hower of death, when our moſt da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous ſtate</l>
                  <l>Requires moſt ſuccour, thou ſtill readie art</l>
                  <l>To croſſe our, then moſt buſie, hellish foe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Guide now our ſteps, and<note n="(e)" place="bottom">Be to me in this life, ô mercifull meeke, and benigne virgin a feruent protectriſſe, &amp; helper, repelling hoſtile attempts, &amp; bringing me to ſaluation, &amp; preſeruing in the laſt moment of my life my miſerable ſoule, &amp; driuing for from it the gaſtly ſights of diuels, but in the terrible day of iudgment freing me, from eternall damnation, &amp; laſtly making me heire to the inacceſsible glorie of thy ſon, and gods <hi>16.</hi>
                     </note> when at deaths pale gate</l>
                  <l>Wee quaking ſtand, force thou our foe't depart,</l>
                  <l>That we to heauen with thee may ioyful goe.</l>
               </lg>
               <note n="(d)" place="bottom">O hope of them who deſpaire <hi>16.</hi>
               </note>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:4919:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 37. REGINA ANGELORVM.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>O QVEENE OF ANGELLS, ſince thy bleſſed child,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe death, true life did to our dead ſouls bring</l>
                  <l>Is (al doe know it) a moſt powerfull thing</l>
                  <l>Thou wel, and iuſtly mayſt a<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Since he who was borne of the virgin is a king, a Lord, and God, therfore the mother which brought him forth is properly, and truly eſteemed a queene, a lady, and mother of God, &amp;c. Atha. m. Euang. de B. V.</note> queene be ſtil'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The higheſt, and moſt glorious Hierarchy</l>
                  <l>Of Angels cannot with thy height compare;</l>
                  <l>The greateſt Angels, and the pureſt that are,</l>
                  <l>Thou doeſt by much ſurpaſſe in purity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O how they al, in thee, thy ſonne admire</l>
                  <l>Who gaue thee ſuch a place, to whoſe great height</l>
                  <l>The great'ſt of them ner'e could, nor can aſpire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Aske thy ſweete ſon, that when with Hell we fight,</l>
                  <l>He would vouchſafe his bleſſed Angels ſend</l>
                  <l>T'helpe vs, our ſoules againſt our foes defend.</l>
               </lg>
               <note n="(b)" place="bottom">O Mary higher, then the bleſſed of heauen, purer then the beames, and glory of the Sunne, more honorable then the Cherubins, and polyomatis. i, many eyed spirits, holyer then the Seraphins, without compariſon more glorious then all the other hoſts of heauen, &amp;c. Ephrem. orat. de laud. B. V. the ſame ſayth Epiphanius ſerm. de land. B. V.</note>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:4919:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 38. REGINA PATRIARCHARVM.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>O QVEENE OF PATRIARCKS, how this bleſſed troope</l>
                  <l>Of fathers wisht to ſee thee whoſe chaſt wombe</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="(a)" place="bottom">O bleſſed virgin, pure doue, and heauenly ſpouſe Mary, heauen, Temple, and throne of the Diuinitie, who haſt for ſonne Chriſt shining gloriouſly in heauen and earth &amp;c. Epiph. ſer. de laud. B. V.</note>The Temple, throne, &amp; heauen should become</l>
                  <l>Of the great power, to which all powers ſtoope.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>On thee their hopes, and expectations laye,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="(b)" place="bottom">All hayle o honour of all prophets, and Patriarchs &amp;c. Andr. Cret. in An. B. V.</note>Thou art the honor, grace, and ornament</l>
                  <l>Of all their name, thou<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Thou didſt not want the purity of Angels, not the fayth of Patriarchs, not the zeale of Apoſtles, not the patience of Martyrs, not the ſobrietie of Confeſſours, not the innocencie or humilitie of Virgins. Idiota. contemp. de Beata V. c. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> not leſſe eminent</l>
                  <l>In the perfection of true faith then they.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou in the whole courſe of thy lif's pure race</l>
                  <l>Them in their owne rar'ſt vertues did'ſt excell</l>
                  <l>And now in glorie doeſt them all ſurpaſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Helpe that wee may, great Queene, ſuch thoughts expell</l>
                  <l>As may againſt vs moue thy ſons dread wrath,</l>
                  <l>And shew vs how to imitate thy Faith.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:4919:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 39. REGINA PROPHETARVM.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>O QVEENE OF PROPHETS, the art that pure white</l>
                  <l>At which the words of theſe great Saints did ayme,</l>
                  <l>How oft haue they, taught by th'alteaching ſpirite</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="(a)" place="bottom">To thee o virgin, the Prophets giue prayſe, &amp;c. Hezych. Hier. orat. de S. Maria Deipara.</note>Extold the glorie of thy ſacred name?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How oft haue they that virgin wisht to ſee</l>
                  <l>Which the<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Hayle armory of life, &amp;c. hayle example of a gemme ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding all price, hayle vine producing faire graps, &amp;c. Chriſoſ. presb. de land. B. V.</note> rare gemme, the fayrgrape bearing vine</l>
                  <l>The armorie of life, the radiant<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Hayle moſt bright ſtar forth of which Chriſt came &amp;c. Ephrem. orat. de land. B. V.</note> ſtarr should be</l>
                  <l>From whence to vs Chriſt's heauenly beames should shine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Noe vertue they nor priuiledge enioy'd,</l>
                  <l>Which on thee (as on farr aboue them all)</l>
                  <l>In farr more great aboundance did not fall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Graunt, gracious queene, our time may be employd</l>
                  <l>So that with theſe bleſt Saints wee euer may</l>
                  <l>To all the world thy matchles worth diſplaye.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:4919:23"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 40. REGINA APOSTOLORVM.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>QVEENE OF TH' APOSTLES, the dread King thy ſonne</l>
                  <l>Being by them, he moſt affected, ſlayne</l>
                  <l>Thou, then the great'ſt on earth (thy ſonne being gone)</l>
                  <l>Didſt Queene &amp; Miſtreſſe to theſe ſaynts remayne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When thou this world chang'dſt for a heauenly croune,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="(a)" place="bottom">We haue receiued by ancient and moſt true tradition, that at the tyme of her glorious departure, all the holy Apoſtles who trauailed the world for the ſaluacion of nations lifted vp on high in a moment mett togeather at Hieruſalem. &amp;c. Euthymius Eremita Hiſt. Eccle. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>40.</hi>
                     </note> All, as at fun'ralls of their ſou'rayne Queene,</l>
                  <l>Though they before to fortaine lands are gone,</l>
                  <l>Preſent at thy bleſt ſepulcher were ſeene.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Although their zeale, as by their actes appeere,</l>
                  <l>Their loue of God and ſanctity was great,</l>
                  <l>Yet they in all, by thee ſurpaſſed were.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy powerfull ſonne, moſt gratious Queene, entreat<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>That at our death we perfectly may ſee</l>
                  <l>How they all ioy, to be ſurpas't by thee.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:4919:23"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 41. REGINA MARTYRVM.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>O Queene of Martyrs who can e're expreſſe</l>
                  <l>The wondrous griefe, which when thy deereſt ſonne</l>
                  <l>To giue his ſeruants life gaue vp his owne,</l>
                  <l>Did all the powers of thy ſoule oppreſſe?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſword of ſorrow which then pearc't thy hart,</l>
                  <l>Cauſd' thee ſuch paines as thou mayſt well compare</l>
                  <l>With greateſt Martyrs:<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Her glory is amongſt martyrs. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Epiph. Hoer. <hi>78.</hi>
                     </note> nay the great'ſt that are</l>
                  <l>Bee farre ſurpaſt by thee, in euery part.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theyr glorie may<note n="(b)" place="bottom">If the Apoſtle Paule doe, truely affirme of other ſaynts whom the world was not worthy of, what is it fitting wee should think of the virgin mother of God, who as farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede all martyrs in brightnes, as doth the ſonne the other ſtarres? Baſil ſeleucius on in Annuntiat. deipar.</note> bee equalled to thyne</l>
                  <l>As may the ſtarres vnto th' irradiant rayes</l>
                  <l>Of ſol, when as he doth moſt clearely shine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If euer Hell death-threatning ſtormes doe rayſe</l>
                  <l>Againſt our conſtancy, thou for vs pray</l>
                  <l>And th' ſuttle force of all ſuch tempeſtes ſtay.</l>
               </lg>
               <note n="(c)" place="bottom">Giue me the effect of my petition &amp; my deſire (o lord) the glorious virgin thy mother Marie my Lady entreating, praying, &amp; preuailing for me with all thy ſaints. Amen. Aug. in medit. c. <hi>35.</hi>
               </note>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:4919:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 42. REGINA CONFESSORVM.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>QVEENE OF CONFESSORS, thy diuine-wrought minde</l>
                  <l>Was with<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Thou didſt not want any kind of vertue, o moſt glorious virgin, not in part but in whole &amp;c. Idiota conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pl. de B. V. c <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> all vertues ſoe exactly dec't,</l>
                  <l>Soe free from ſinne, ſoe voyde of all defect,</l>
                  <l>As ſinnes, to thee th' world could no equall finde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who had a more firme liuely fayth then thou?</l>
                  <l>Who was more glad, more ready for that fayth</l>
                  <l>To ſuffer paines? the cruell'ſt tyrant's wrath</l>
                  <l>Could n'ere haue force thy conſtancy to bowe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The great'ſt Confeſſor neuer did excell</l>
                  <l>In any vertue<note n="(c)" place="bottom">In thee all vertues as well actiue, as contemplatiue mett to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather, and make then more admirable thee all creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. <hi>16.</hi>
                     </note> which we do not ſee</l>
                  <l>T'haue shin'd more truely, and more full in thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Obtayne we may our ſoules adorne ſoe well</l>
                  <l>With theſe thy vertues that when as we dye</l>
                  <l>We may through thee the deuill's force defye.</l>
               </lg>
               <note n="(b)" place="bottom">There neither is, nor euer was, nor will be any sport of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne in thee either Originall, or actuall, or mortall or veniall: but thou haſt all grace of Naturall benefitts, spirituall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and celeſtiall guiftes, ibidem.</note>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:4919:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 43 REGINA VIRGINVM.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>O QVEENE OF VIRGINS, thou the glorius<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Thou art the ornament, crowne, &amp; ioy of virgins. Ephraem. our. de laud. B. V.</note> croune</l>
                  <l>And chief'ſt grace art of that ſpottles ſtate;</l>
                  <l>Thy<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Certaine men affirme that Marie married after the birth (of our ſauiour) but they haue not any means to proue it, for thoſe ſonns who weare ſayd to be of Ioſeph, were not borne of Marie, neither is there any ſcripture which makes mention of it. Orig. in Luc. homil. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note> ſacred wombe to man was neuer knowne!</l>
                  <l>Yet hee's thy child, whoe doeth Hell's pride abate:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou though a mother, yet without compare</l>
                  <l>Then pureſt virgins waſt by farre more pure</l>
                  <l>From the deceits of each intrapping ſnare:</l>
                  <l>Thy thoughts, words, deedes were euer all ſecure:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>None but thy greateſt ſonne whoſe wondrous birth</l>
                  <l>Did not at all thy virgin-bands<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Vide mater Caſtiſsima at <hi>(a).</hi>
                     </note> vntye,</l>
                  <l>Deſerued<note n="(d)" place="bottom">Marie was moſt cleare wooll, &amp; moſt renouned for virginity, &amp; (vithous compariſon) purer then all the virgins which were vnder heauen and the was ſuch an one, and of ſo great excellency that she alone deſerued this noe other should be cloſed with her, but he who was of Royall dignity. Aleuimus de Trinitate. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
                     </note> in thy virgin wombe to lye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Vouchſafe (chaſt queene) while yet we liue on Earth,</l>
                  <l>With all bleſt Virgins which ſtill waite on thee,</l>
                  <l>Before thy ſonne our aduocate to bee.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="sonnet">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:4919:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET</hi> 44. REGINA SANCTORVM OMNIVM.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>QVeene of all Saints, ô ſupreame gouerneſſe</l>
                  <l>Next to thy ſonne, of all thy ſonne hath made:</l>
                  <l>But onely he noe other can be ſayd</l>
                  <l>Soe powerfull as thy ſelfe, Hell's force t' repreſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou not all women onely didſt<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Shee is holy and holyer then all Saynes: &amp;c. Damaſc. or. <hi>2.</hi> de g<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rmine meo &amp;c.</note> excell</l>
                  <l>In vertue, but th' great'ſt ſaynts, yea<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Shee is holy and holyer then all Saynes: &amp;c. Damaſc. or. <hi>2.</hi> de g<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rmine meo &amp;c.</note> all that are:</l>
                  <l>Th' Æternall thee, his mountaine, did prepare</l>
                  <l>On topp of mountaines, there him ſelfe to dwel.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In fine there is 'twix't other ſaynts and thee,</l>
                  <l>As great a diff'rence, as betwixt the taſte</l>
                  <l>And ſmell of th' moſt delicious fruits that bee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Make interceſſion that wee may be plac't</l>
                  <l>Great Queene, among theſe ſaynts with them to ſing.</l>
                  <l>Th' immortall prayſes of thy ſonne, our King.</l>
               </lg>
               <note n="(a)" place="bottom">God did not chooſe any of the ordinary ſex of women to be his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but her, who should ſurpaſſe all women in vertue. Iuſtinut queſt. <hi>136.</hi>
               </note>
               <note n="(c)" place="bottom">Is not Marie a high Mountayne &amp;c. for Iſayas prophecying of the moſt excellent dignity of this mountayne, ſayth: The mountaine of our Lord shall in the latter daye: be prepared in the topp of mountaines. Suerly there was a mountaine in the top of mountaynes, becauſe the height of Marie shin'd gloriously aboue all Saynes. Greg. mag. l. <hi>1.</hi> Reg. c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:4919:26"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
